<lee>
  <node id="'$doc_root'">
    <doc lang="en">
      <section id="quick-start">
        <title>Quick start</title>
        <para>Start 100 clients connecting to localhost with 10ms pause in between. Clients publish a 1kb-size message every 10ms to topic <code>t/%clientid%</code>. Run steady traffic for 30s and then exit:</para>
        <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
emqttb --loiter 30s @pub --topic 't/%n' --conninterval 10ms --pubinterval 10ms --num-clients 100 --size 1kb @g --host 127.0.0.1
]]></programlisting>
        <para>Same with shortened arguments:</para>
        <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
emqttb -L 30s @pub -t 't/%n' -I 10ms -i 10ms -N 100 -s 1kb @g -h 127.0.0.1
]]></programlisting>
        <para>Start 10 clients that subscribe to a wildcard topic and run steady traffic for 30s:</para>
        <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
emqttb --loiter 30s  @sub --topic 't/#' --conninterval 10ms --num-clients 10 @g --host 127.0.0.1
]]></programlisting>
        <para>Same with shortened arguments:</para>
        <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
emqttb -L 30s @sub -t 't/#' -I 10ms -N 10 @g -h 127.0.0.1
]]></programlisting>
        <para>Combine the above scenarios in a single command:</para>
        <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
emqttb -L 30s  @pub -t 't/%n' -I 10ms -i 10ms -N 100 -s 1kb @sub -t 't/#' -I 10ms -N 10 @g -h 127.0.0.1
]]></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section id="intro-running">
        <title>Understanding EMQTTB CLI</title>
        <para>
          EMQTTB executable accepts named CLI arguments (such as <code>--foo</code> or <code>-f</code>), positional arguments and <emphasis>actions</emphasis>.
          Actions are special CLI arguments that start with <code>@</code> character (e.g. <code>@my-action</code>).
          Actions correspond to different load-generation scenarios, such as <code>@pub</code> and <code>@sub</code>, <link linkend='groups'>client group</link> configurations and <link linkend="autorate">autorates</link>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Each CLI action defines its own <emphasis>scope</emphasis> of named and positional CLI arguments.
          Positional arguments are always specified after named arguments within the scope.
          There is also a <emphasis>global</emphasis> scope of arguments that don't belong to any action.
          Global arguments are specified before the very first action.
        </para>
        <para>
          Example:
          <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
emqttb --foo --bar 1 positional1 positional2 @action1 --foo 1 positional1 @action2 ...
       |___________| |_____________________|          |_________________|
       |regular args    positional args    |            action1 scope
       |___________________________________|
                 global scope
]]></programlisting>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="concepts">
        <title>Core concepts</title>
        <para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Worker</emphasis> a process that corresponds
                to a single MQTT client
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Behavior</emphasis> a callback module
                containing functions that workers run in a loop
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Group</emphasis> a supervised colletion of
                workers running the same behavior and sharing the same
                configuration.  Group manager controls the number of
                workers, restarts failed workers and implements ramp
                up/down logic.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Scenario</emphasis> a callback module that
                creates several worker groups and manupulates group
                configuration using autorate.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Autorate</emphasis> a process that adjusts
                group parameters (such as number of workers in the
                group, or worker configuration) based on constants or
                dynamic parameters, e.g. available RAM or CPU load,
                observed latency and so on.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Client group configuration</title>
        <para>
          Load generation scenarios (such as <code>@pub</code> and
          <code>@sub</code>) don't explicitly specify how the clients
          should connect to the MQTT broker. These settings are
          delegated to <link linkend="cli-command-g">group
          configuration</link>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Each group configuration has an id.
          EMQTTB always creates a default group with id=<code>default</code>.
          All scenarios use it by default.
        </para>
        <para>
          Scenarios use group configuration for each client group they
          create. For example, <code>@pub</code> scenario creates only
          one group for publishers which is specified by
          <code>--group</code> or <code>-g</code> CLI
          argument. Usually this scenario is invoked with implicit
          <code>default</code> group configuration:

        <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
emqttb @pub -t foo @g -h localhost
]]></programlisting>
          It is equivalent to the following command:
        <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
emqttb @pub -t foo --group default @g --group default -h localhost
]]></programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
          Sometimes it is necessary to use different group
          configurations for different scenarios.  For example,
          imagine we need to test pub/sub scenario where publishers
          use websocket connections and subscribers use MQTT, or we
          want to test bridging between MQTT brokers that have
          different hostnames. It can be achieved like this:
        <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
emqttb @pub -t 'foo/%n' -g wss \
       @sub -t 'foo/#' -g mqtt \
       @g -g wss -h localhost --transport ws --ssl \
       @g -g mqtt -h localhost --transport sock
]]></programlisting>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Metrics</title>
        <para>
          EMQTTB can export metrics to Prometheus using pushgateway or scraping REST endpoint.
          Scraping endpoint is enabled automatically when the script is started with <code>--restapi</code> global flag.
          Pushgateway should be enabled explicitly:
        <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
emqttb --pushgw --pushgw-url http://localhost:9091
]]></programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
          There is a ready-to-use grafana dashboard for emqttb: <ulink url="https://github.com/ieQu1/grafana-dashboards/blob/master/grafana/dashboards/emqttb-dashboard.json">emqttb-dashboard.json</ulink>.
          Also there is a fully ready docker images that include Grafana and Postgres with all the necessary schemas and dashboards for emqttb and emqx performance analysis:
          <ulink url="https://github.com/ieQu1?tab=packages&amp;repo_name=grafana-dashboards">github.com/ieQu1/grafana-dashboards</ulink>
        </para>
        <para>
          Additionally, EMQTTB can add annotations to grafana dashboards when scenarios start, advance to a next stage or finish.
          This requires a Grafana API key with <code>Editor</code> role.
          Once the key is obtained, it can be used like this:
          <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[
export EMQTTB_METRICS__GRAFANA__API_KEY="Bearer eyJrIjoiNmhSdTFnWGJlaE9tZXQ2YXI4WlEyUGNSMXFMb1oyUXkiLCJuIjoiZW1xdHRiIiwiaWQiOjF9"
export EMQTTB_METRICS__GRAFANA__URL="http://localhost:3000"
emqttb --grafana ...
]]></programlisting>
        </para>
      </section>
    </doc>
  </node>
  <node id="autorate">
    <doc lang="en">
      <para>
        When the loadgen creates too much traffic, the system may get overloaded.
        In this case, the test usually has to be restarted all over again with different parameters.
        This can be very expensive in man-hours and computing resources.
      </para>
      <para>
        In order to prevent that, emqttb can tune some parameters (such as message publishing interval)
        automatically using
        <link xlink:href="https://controlguru.com/integral-reset-windup-jacketing-logic-and-the-velocity-pi-form/">PI contoller</link>
      </para>
    </doc>
  </node>
  <node id="interval">
    <doc lang="en">
      <para>
        It is possible to specify time unit as <emphasis>ms</emphasis>, <emphasis>us</emphasis> or <emphasis>s</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </doc>
  </node>
  <node id="autorate/{}/id">
    <doc lang="en">
      <para>
        Autorate configuration can be referred by id.
      </para>
    </doc>
  </node>
  <node id="scenarios/emqttb_scenario_pub">
    <doc lang="en">
      <section>
        <title>Description</title>
        <para>
          This scenario starts <code>-N</code> workers, which publish messages to the specified topic at period <code>--pubinterval</code>.
          The only mandatory parameter is <code>--topic</code>, which supports pattern substitutions.
        </para>
        <para>
          Configuration of the publishers (such as broker hostname and port, tcp settings, etc.) is delegated to
          <link linkend='groups'/>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>
        <section>
          <title>Basic usage</title>
          <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[emqttb @pub -t foo/%n -N 100 -i 10ms -s 1kb]]></programlisting>
          <para>
            In this example the loadgen connects to the default broker <link xlink:href="mqtt://localhost:1883"/>,
            starts 100 publishers which send messages to topic with the suffix of the worker id every 10 milliseconds. Size of the messages is 1kb.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Changing client settings</title>
          <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[emqttb @pub -t foo/%n @g --ssl --transport ws -h 127.0.0.1]]></programlisting>
          <para>
            In this example settings of the default client group has been changed: TLS encryption is enabled, and WebSocket transport is used.
            Also the hostname of the broker is specified explicitly.
          </para>
          <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[emqttb @pub -t foo/%n -q 1 -g pub @g -g pub --ssl --transport ws -h 127.0.0.1]]></programlisting>
          <para>
            The below example is similar to the previous one, except QoS of the messages is set to 1,
            and a dedicated client configuration with id <code>pub</code> is used for the publishers.
            It's useful for running multiple scenarios (e.g. <code>@pub</code> and <code>@sub</code>) in parallel, when they must use
            different settings. For example, it can be used for testing MQTT bridge.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Tuning publishing rate automatically</title>
          <para>
            By default, <code>@pub</code> scenario keeps <code>pubinterval</code> constant.
            However, in some situations it should be tuned dynamically: suppose one wants to measure what publishing rate the broker can sustain while keeping
            publish latency under <code>--publatency</code>.
          </para>
          <para>
            This is also useful for preventing system overload.
            Generating too much load can bring the system down, and the test has to be started all over again with different parameters.
            Sometimes finding the correct rate takes many attempts, wasting human and machine time.
            Dynamic tuning of the publishing rate for keeping the latency constant can help in this situation.
          </para>
          <para>
            By default the maximum speed of rate adjustment is set to 0, effectively locking the <code>pubinterval</code> at a constant value.
            To enable automatic tuning, the autorate speed <code>-V</code> must be set to a non-zero value, also it makes sense to set
            the minimum (<code>-m</code>) and maximum (<code>-M</code>) values of the <code>pubinterval</code>:
          </para>
          <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[emqttb @pub -t foo -i 1s -q 1 --publatency 50ms @a -V 10 -m 0 -M 10000]]></programlisting>
          <para>
            Once automatic adjustment of the publishing interval is enabled, <code>-i</code> parameter sets the starting value of the publish interval,
            rather than the constant value. So the above example reads like this:
          </para>
          <para>
            Publish messages to topic <code>foo</code> with QoS 1, starting at the publishing interval of 1000 milliseconds, dynamically adjusting it
            so to keep the publishing latency around 50 milliseconds. The publishing interval is kept between 0 and 10 seconds,
            and the maximum rate of its change is 10 milliseconds per second.
          </para>
          <para>
            For more information about the automatic parameter tuning see <link linkend="autorate"/>.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </doc>
  </node>
  <node id="scenarios/emqttb_scenario_pubsub_forward">
    <doc lang="en">
      <section>
        <title>Description</title>
        <para>
          First all subscribers connect and subscribe to the brokers, then
          the publishers start to connect and publish.  The default is to use
          full forwarding of messages between the nodes: that is, each
          publisher client publishes to a topic subscribed by a single
          client, and both clients reside on distinct nodes.
        </para>
        <para>
          Full forwarding of messages is the default and can be set by <link linkend="full_forwarding"/>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>
        <section>
          <title>Basic usage</title>
          <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[./emqttb --restapi @pubsub_fwd --publatency 10ms --num-clients 400 -i 70ms @g -h 172.25.0.2:1883,172.25.0.3:1883,172.25.0.4:1883]]></programlisting>
          <para>
            In this example the loadgen connects to a list of brokers
            in a round-robin in the declared order.  First all the
            subscribers, then the publishers, with the difference that
            publishers will shift the given host list by one position
            to ensure each publisher and subscriber pair will reside
            on different hosts, thus forcing all messages to be
            forwarded.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </doc>
  </node>
  <node id="scenarios/emqttb_scenario_pub/{}/topic">
    <doc lang="en">
      <para>
        Topic is a mandatory parameter. It supports the following substitutions:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>%n</code> is replaced with the worker ID (integer)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>%g</code> is replaced with the group ID</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>%h</code> is replaced with the hostname</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </doc>
  </node>
  <node id="scenarios/emqttb_scenario_persistent_session/{}/pub/qos">
    <doc lang="en">
      <para>
        Warning: changing QoS to any value other then 2 is likely to cause consume stage to hang,
        since it has to consume the exact number of messages as previously produced.
      </para>
    </doc>
  </node>
  <node id="scenarios/emqttb_scenario_persistent_session/{}/sub/qos">
    <doc lang="en">
      <para>
        Warning: changing QoS to any value other then 2 is likely to cause consume stage to hang,
        since it has to consume the exact number of messages as previously produced.
      </para>
    </doc>
  </node>
  <node id="groups/{}/client/clientid">
    <doc lang="en">
      <para>
        A pattern used to generate ClientID. The following substitutions are supported:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>%n</code> is replaced with the worker ID (integer)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>%g</code> is replaced with the group ID</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>%h</code> is replaced with the hostname</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </doc>
  </node>
</lee>
